Professor
David Cheg here. When using line
notation to depict molecules, we
sometimes disregard the true geometry of
the molecule by flattening it out. But
if we are depicting molecules with their
true geometry, substituents must be on
wedge or dash bonds in order to obey the
tetrahedral geometry that these sp3
centers demand. And with that we have
set the stage for an important concept.
The notion of stereoisomerism
and kirality. We already know what
structural isomers are. These are
molecules that have the same molecular
formula but differing connectivity. This
would be like a straight chain alkan
versus a branched alkan with the same
number of carbons or even something like
dimethyl ether versus ethanol which
produces different functional groups.
But even when molecules have precisely
the same connectivity, we can still have
stereoisomeism.
Stereo isomers are molecules that have
the same molecular formula and the same
connectivity but differ in the way the
atoms are distributed in space. Take
this molecule two bromoane. This brmo
group must be on either a dash bond or a
wedge bond as we know. But if we draw
both options, we must understand that
these are not the same molecule. They
are mirror images of one another. If we
take this one on the wedge bond and
reflect it across this mirror plane, we
get this mirror image. And if we then
flip it over to the other side to try to
line up the main chain, this brmo group
pointing towards us will end up pointing
away from us and therefore on a dash
bond and will not line up with this
first bromo group. These molecules are
mirror images just like your hands are
mirror images. Your hands are not
superposable. That is to say, if one
hand is placed over the other with the
palms facing the same direction, we
can't get the fingers to line up
properly. When a molecule is not
superposable on its mirror image in
precisely this manner, this molecule is
said to be chyro and specifically this
carbon is said to be a chyro center.
There are a lot of synonyms for this
term. We could say stereo center or
stereogenic center and we'd be talking
about the same thing. We would generally
be talking about a carbon atom that is
connected to four different groups. In
this case, methyl, ethyl, bromemo,
hydrogen. This is the reason the mirror
image is different. If we changed this
ethl to a methyl, when we get the mirror
image, we would find that it is
absolutely identical. This is due to the
internal symmetry of the molecule.
Because the mirror image is identical,
this molecule is not chyal, which we can
also call a chyro. It will be very
important to be able to identify chyro
centers. Take a look at this molecule.
Take a moment and see if you can
identify all the chyro centers. Bear in
mind that sp and sp2 hybridized carbons
will not qualify. We are almost always
talking about sp3 carbons when referring
to chyro centers. Also remember that
hydrogen atoms bound to carbon are
implied and not shown. So we must keep
these in mind as well when considering
the four groups bound to any carbon. Are
you ready? Here are all the chyro
centers in this molecule marked with an
asterisk. Each of the four groups bound
to these carbons is different. Either
different elements or different kinds of
carbon chains that are not precisely
identical. We must be able to do this
with any organic molecule.
So we should now understand what is
meant by the term chyro as well as a
chyro center on a molecule and be able
to identify such chyal centers on any
molecule. Professor Dave for CHEG. See
you next time.